[snorts]
>> One of the precepts is about training in
regards to abstaining from intoxicants.
And the Buddha did not list any specific
items, and my impression is that some
modern so-called drugs do not fall into
the category of an intoxicant such as
LSD, ayahuasca, and so on.
They have been used for a long time in
ancient cultures as medicine to open you
up to a higher reality and become more
receptive for spiritual values.
In addition, they are used therapeutic
these days in ceremonies or as
microdosing in psychotherapy.
All this seems to indicate that they are
no intoxicants. They rather heal than
destroy. But I still have doubts if the criteria
But I still have doubts if the criteria
for intoxication that I apply are
correct. Is it only the results and side
effects that something has?
Or is there a broader intoxication that
underlies this?
Uh so, the problem is the effect, for
sure. Um
Um
the thing is
you have two sides to that coin. So,
there is the
um
what that person called opening up to a
higher reality,
um
which is how it appears.
And then there is the
effect that it has on your mind,
which is the more important thing.
And uh the effect that it has is putting
you out of touch
with the ordinary reality,
the ordinary reality,
which is where your problems actually
are. Your problems were not in the higher
Your problems were not in the higher
reality. They were in in this reality
that you're trying to to
uh transcend.
So, you don't transcend it by replacing
it with a different reality.
You transcend it by understanding
and overcoming
the craving that you have in regard to
the unpleasant things that manifest in
this reality.
And whatever you discover in a different
reality cannot have any effect
whatsoever on this reality and your mind's attitude
on this reality and your mind's attitude
towards this reality. So,
it's kind of like saying
um
you you
you will solve the problems that you
experience um
um
at your workplace
by going on vacation.
Like sure, you will stop experiencing
the the
acute um
um
disturbances and people harassing you
and stuff just because you went on a
vacation, but there is absolutely noth-
nothing being done about the root cause
of the disturbance when you are at work.
So, the reason why you have to abstain from
the reason why you have to abstain from
these intoxicants not just because
if it were just a temporary
disconnection, just a temporary
vacation, that would be fine.
But, the thing is
by taking intoxicants, you are training
this uh habit that you already have,
that everybody already has,
of of resolving their problems
by going elsewhere, by changing the
scenery, by um
yeah, going out of touch with them.
Just becoming oblivious about them.
becoming oblivious about them.
And um
that there's a reason why that's
appealing. Like it's not just it's not a
it's not a
there's a reason why drugs are such a a
a pre- prevalent thing that people
resort to. It's because
it it the mind wants that kind of
escape. Escape through distraction, escape
Escape through distraction, escape
through replacement.
Um and then it just some people are
willing to go very far with that
attitude of distraction and replacement
and oblivion.
To the point where they become out
alcoholics or drug addicts and so on.
So, it's completely irrelevant whether
it gives you these side effects of
you know, health issues and and all
that. The what matters is in terms of
the dhamma is how it's training the
attitude again that you already start
with is just making it worse.
Of uh not facing
suffering, not facing discomfort,
understanding it, and removing your
craving in regard to it. It's training
the the habit of just
replacing the thing that causes you
suffering with something else. So, whatever higher
with something else. So, whatever higher
reality you encounter,
uh you might feel a relief
because of that.
Because the the
the content that was triggering your
craving changed.
And it sort of fills you with this
novelty. But in actuality, the same
But in actuality, the same
hindrances, the same craving, the same
inclinations of the mind are still
there. You just don't see them as an
issue in this particular case
because of the novelty, because of the
the the yeah, temporary relief that it gives
the yeah, temporary relief that it gives
you.
But if you were to stay there long
enough, if that became your new reality
constantly, you would eventually realize whatever
you would eventually realize whatever
higher reality I go to,
the same problem remains cuz it wasn't
in the content of my perceptions. It's
in how my mind craved.
So, um
um
however far you go in in with that type
of escape, which by the way is the same
thing that people would try to get from
their meditation,
um and it's just a completely misguided
endeavor. Um,
Um,
whatever escape you go to, it has this
um, appeal because of this contrast that
it has with your ordinary reality. So,
it's just a replacement
that relieves the tension
just because it's different.
But, replacing the content does nothing
about why was the previous content an issue in
why was the previous content an issue in
the first place.
So, as I said, it's a matter of time.
However, whatever replacement you do,
it's like, you know, when when you're
when you've been living in the same
house, in the same neighborhood, in the
same country
for decades,
and then you get the option to go
somewhere else, it's going to feel like
this uh, you're going to feel excited, you're
uh, you're going to feel excited, you're
going to feel like, oh, I'm going to be
able to escape all these issues finally,
and so on.
And yeah, for the first few
however long you live there, there
there's going to be a time, this this
honeymoon phase, almost,
where you still have a strong enough memory of
you still have a strong enough memory of
those previous issues that this feels
like it's it's not there anymore. The
problems have gone away. But,
eventually, because the mind is not
trained, you will find yourself in the
exact same position position again.
So, that's why it's not a resolution at
all, and it's actually
a deviation from the practice. So, it's
when you go to the point of taking
toxicants, you're actually not just, uh,
you're actually not just, uh,
making a uh, a choice of replacing
circumstances, which you you will do to
some extent, it's now a view, comes with
a view,
that this is a valid way to resolve your
suffering. And that's just a very coarse, uh,
And that's just a very coarse, uh,
example. You have also, for example,
entertainment. Entertainment is the same principle.
Entertainment is the same principle.
It's like, by watching a movie, by
listening to music, by absorbing
yourself in pleasant conversation with
um people you like and so on.
It gives you this this change of scenery
where you don't have to deal with
whatever issues were weighing on you.
And it cultivates the exact same habit
of um dealing with suffering by looking
away from it.
So, that's why that's also
um a a a a more subtle form, but it's a
it's a restraint that is required for
the same reason.
So, it's it's to
um
undo the habit of delusion, which is the
the habit of delusion, which is the
third defilement. And in fact
the Buddha said it's it's not just very
uh hard to get rid of, but it's also
very blameworthy.
Very prob- problematic
because it's the root for the other two.
So, sometimes people have this notion
that well, look, I'm not
uh uh
um
lustfully chasing after sensual objects.
I'm not
angry and and so on. So, this is fine.
Like uh yeah, watching movies or even
uh yeah, watching movies or even
intoxication with these spiritual drugs.
Um and they don't realize that delusion
is actually more harmful
than the other two
because see, you wouldn't be resorting to
see, you wouldn't be resorting to
sensuality. You wouldn't be resorting to
ill will as a means of resolving your
suffering unless you already had the view
unless you already had the view
that changing the circumstances
and that just uh replacing the content
of what you experience is a valid
solution. So,
So,
by feeding that view
you're feeding the potential for lust
and aversion, even if it's not there
right now.
You're feeding the root that allows it
to grow
when those uh sens- sense objects hit.
Your mind will be craving that
replacement. So, like you find yourself
with a displeasure of seeing a sensual
object, you want to replace that
experience with
going for the sensual object, getting
more of it.
Uh when something unpleasant strikes
you, uh and that's factual.
uh and that's factual.
That's That's just how the experience
come comes up, but then you crave to
replace it
with a more pleasant experience that doesn't
a more pleasant experience that doesn't
have that
uh unpleasant thing anymore.
So, that's what I mean. It trains the same
that's what I mean. It trains the same
fundamental habit. Delusion trains the
same fundamental habit
that that is the basis for the other two
types of defilement.
Could one say then that that's the this
principle of wanting to change the
scenery, wanting to replace one
experience with another?
Is the criteria to judge whether things
are an intoxicant or not?
Cuz people obviously they can come up
with lists and items that they think
that are intoxicants,
which maybe even science might say they
are intoxicants, but if you look at that
principle, they might actually turn out
not to be intoxicants. And other things
that are not seen as intoxicants
are actually intoxicants. Yeah, well,
for instance, I think even things like
coffee would be regarded as an
intoxicant because it
changes your brain chemistry or or and
whatnot, but
the thing is
nobody would go for coffee as a means of
forgetting about your problems.
Like it's it's it it just doesn't have
that effect. It doesn't put you out of
touch with the ordinary reality.
with the ordinary reality.
Uh whereas yeah, alcohol,
uh cannabis,
spiritual drugs, LSD, mushrooms,
uh DMT, all these things
that people might think have a spiritual
benefit, they do have that effect and that's
they do have that effect and that's
exactly why people would resort to them
out of wrong views
as a means to resolve
the ordinary reality.
So, um,
um,
yeah, exactly. You can't rely on a list
because God knows how many drugs there are.
God knows how many drugs there are.
But,
what you have to rely on is
basically, if you already see yourself
inclined towards it because of this
uh, promise that it will help you forget
about things, that it will give you
something else that's better, a
different kind of experience that's
better than what you currently have,
that's delusion already.
You're trying to overcome what is
actually still there cuz it get like I
said, it's not that your your
defilements are are disappearing because
you replace the experience, they're just
covered up. They become less obvious.
So, um,
um,
if if if that's the appeal of it, then
it's an intoxicant.
Or or that's the effect of it even if
you're not
um, thinking about it. Other people are
pressuring into it, whatever it might
be, but you know that the effect will be
that you'll be put into this this um,
different state
where uh, you don't have to deal as much
uh, you don't have to deal as much
with the pressures and um,
sort of
um, discomforts of ordinary reality.
discomforts of ordinary reality.
That's an intoxicant. So then, that
means it doesn't necessarily need to be
even a uh, uh, um, consumable substance.
Like I said before, meditation
uh, in the way that's presented in most
traditions today
is precisely that. It's a way to
be out of touch
with where the actual problem is,
resolving it temporarily,
but then you know, people expect that
the solution will come by experiencing
an even more special than the already
special state that they have. They just
keep chasing that after eventually it's
chasing that after eventually it's
special enough and that's going to
resolve the issue.
Failing to see that
it's those very habits of the mind
that manifest when they're not in Well,
that become more obvious when they're
not in those special states.
That's where the problem is.
Like the fact that they that their mind
can be upset
by um
annoying situations. The fact that the
mind can be
entranced by pleasant things that arise
when they're not in a a hypnotic state.
That's the issue and they're doing
absolutely nothing about it
by replacing the content of their
experience with these more special types
that just cover up the problem.
And they would see as well
obviously the thing is
they don't want to see it,
but they would see that those habits of
lust, those habits of of longing, habits of
those habits of of longing, habits of
expectation,
of anticipation, of
desire are still underlying all those efforts
are still underlying all those efforts
to chase after a special experience.
It's just that it doesn't count because
the content is different.
But obviously that's the wrong criteria
cuz the mind
is not the the state of mind is not
determined by what it is chasing after.
It's the attitude of chasing
that's the issue.
That's what keeps you bound to samsara
and to suffering.
But I mean someone could say in the in
the context of caffeine for example,
like you are tired,
you are averse to the tiredness, Mhm.
and you want to replace that experience
with the experience of being charged,
being vital, feeling alive.
Obviously being functional as well and
so on and so forth.
But there seems to be a at least to some
there seems to be a at least to some
degree a correlation that you are not
happy with the present state and you
take something.
But obviously that
principle can applies almost to
anything. >> Yeah, that's why anything could have a
>> Yeah, that's why anything could have a
degree of unwholesomeness behind it.
So if you're taking caffeine because you
can't deal
with tiredness and you feel confined by
it, then that right there is an opportunity
then that right there is an opportunity
for training.
But the point is like you wouldn't be
resorting to that in and of itself
as like it doesn't in and of itself put
you out of touch with reality.
So
it's like
um
it doesn't make you it's let's say you
have you're dealing dealing with
um
I don't know issues in your
interpersonal relationships
or
uh
pain or or sadness or depression whatever.
or or sadness or depression whatever.
This is not going to
put you and and and change the content
of your thoughts and allow you to avoid
all those memories and regrets or
whatever you might have.
So yeah, it can anything can serve like
you could say you eat
you eat food. The food helps you avoid
the state of hunger.
Um
and that's just the principle of action
like whenever you do anything you're
trying to replace the present state of
affairs. But the thing is
But the thing is
there's a difference between replacing
the present state of affairs and going
out of touch
with the
the
let's say the the the base where dukkha
arises. Like so Like so
um
that base meaning
sight, sound, smells, taste, touches.
The six sense bases.
Which the Buddha said, that's what you
have to understand.
That's where the problem arises.
You go out of that, or well, you don't
go out of it, but you
you replace the content enough
for you to not have to be
concerned with it anymore, not to have
to be concerned with understanding it.
So, it's like a you arrive at the
solution through the completely wrong
place. You don't need to
You don't need to
overcome the craving anymore. You don't
experience the suffering because the
thing changed. So,
that's what you have to
um
avoid. Not think, oh, every action that I do is
Not think, oh, every action that I do is
an issue because I'm replacing the
present state of affairs. It's like am I
still going to be
able or have a
have the need to understand
the root of the problem, understand
suffering, overcome craving in order to
deal with the issue, in order to escape
the issue,
or am I just escaped Do I just escape
circumstantially by changing the scenery as as I said,
by changing the scenery as as I said,
which means when I fail to change the
scenery, that's it. I'm done. I'm back to where I
that's it. I'm done. I'm back to where I
started. So,
So,
with things that are not intoxicants,
you will see
it's going to leave you plenty of of
need to understand suffering in order to not
to understand suffering in order to not
not experience it.
Cuz yeah, you might get rid of the
tiredness, um
um
and then, but something else will come
up. So, it's not like it's it's uh removing
So, it's not like it's it's uh removing
that opportunity.
It's not putting you completely out of
touch where this
with the space where these things can
strike you.
And then you're forced to be developed
enough to not be
uh
affected by them.
Would be in another way of thinking
about it is
like if you let's say
on the subjects of old age, sickness,
death, losing something that's dear to you.
losing something that's dear to you.
You would never resort to caffeine.
Yeah, to
forget about it.
You would resolve certainly to
alcohol, drugs,
company, and distractions, and entertainment, but
and distractions, and entertainment, but
things that
yeah, might change
the experience, but not like you said to
the degree that you are actually
forgetting about those issues. I mean,
standing up, sitting down, going to
sleep, brushing your teeth, taking medicine,
brushing your teeth, taking medicine,
all these things would change the
experience. But it doesn't it doesn't put you out of
But it doesn't it doesn't put you out of
the place where
like I said, things can strike you.
And and where it's obvious that you haven't
and where it's obvious that you haven't
developed yourself.
And it's not developing a habit of
delusion, not by itself at least, and
not as strongly,
which is the habit of resolving the
issue by changing the scenery.
Or well, the habit of
thinking that you can resolve the issue
by changing the scenery.
Thinking that you can overcome suffering
by resolving by changing the scenery.
If it was clear to you that that's not
possible, then it would be impossible for you to
then it would be impossible for you to
resort to intoxication, to resort to
entertainment. But it wouldn't be impossible for you to
But it wouldn't be impossible for you to
drink caffeine, to stand up,
to brush your teeth, to take medicine.
Cuz you're not expecting that to be a
result to be a resolution.